[Music]
We're talking about resolutions. First
one is temporary resolution
48-25. A resolution authorizes service
safety director to participate in the
Ohio public works commission state
capital improvement and/or local
transportation improvement programs to
execute contracts as required and to
declare an emergency. This is coming
from public works committee and
Councilman uh Diner. Yes. I'm going to
have Kurt come up and explain this. This
is something we really need to get past
so we can move ahead with the project.
Good evening. Um, so last fall or maybe
even last summer, we came to you for
legislation to apply for a grant for the
OPWC money for Arbor Valley
Drive. What we failed to put in that
legislation was that uh we were
authorized to enter into
agreements which we need to get the
grant. So, the folks that are um
awarding the project let me know that
the legislation that we gave them last
fall was missing uh that permission to
enter into an agreement. Um so, in order
to get that back quickly so that we
might get those uh grant monies, we've
asked for emergency and one reading to
enter into the agreement that I think
we're going to
get. Any questions?
Maggie. Nope. Thank you. Nope. I don't.
Um Corey Skooner will be my second and I
believe you're going to ask for
suspension tonight if that's okay with
everybody so we can get this in so we
can any objections from council.
Okay. Thanks, Kurt. All right.
Temporary resolution
49-25, a resolution to increase receipts
and appropriate from the unencumbered
balance. Amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriations with the
county auditor in the general
fund for the one-time strategic
community investment grant program and
to declare an emergency. Uh this is
coming from uh finance committee and
uh who's going to speak on that?
[Music]
Uh Chairman Wolfinger, I'm happy to
speak to that if you'd like. I was
hiding. You're behind the mayor. I look
down. You're not there.
So this is a grant that uh was actually
written uh last year by our community
development director, Linda Berky
Disser, who I saw out in the audience.
So huge thanks to her for writing this
grant. Um so now it is actually time for
us to receive the grant and receive the
funds and to do that we needed to um do
legislation to accept the money and
appropriate the money.
Very good. Any
questions? And um Councilman, you'll be
my second and we'll do three readings.
Thank you.
Temporary resolution
50-25, a resolution to authorize the
service safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding for a sole source
provider contract for membrane
replacement for the south water plant
coming from water water pollution
control. Councilman Wing. Yes. Thank
you, Mr. Chairman. I'd like to invite
Denise Cruz up here to give a little bit
of a background on this piece, but um
essentially this begins the process of a
rotation to um replace the membranes of
the north and south water plants
or south. Yes, South. Oh, yes. South.
Yeah. Good evening. It's because it
started at the North Water Plant. Um, a
couple months ago we looked at switching
the membranes
um that we were going to install at the
Northwater plant and that turned into a
bigger issue than we expected. But in
the meantime, the membrane manufacturer
was willing to give us a good deal on
the membranes that we could use at the
Southwater plant. So, um, those
membranes are the original membranes
from 2002.
Um the um membrane manufacturer is very
interested in that because they want to
know why they lasted so long. Um so this
will allow us to buy approximately 500
membranes. Um I think it's slightly
under and um start membrane replacement
plant plan at the South Water plant. So
over the next several years we'll be
buying membranes and change out each
skid as we go along. and then we'll
switch and do the Northwater plant. So,
this is actually going to turn into an
ongoing project um as part of our asset
management program. But in this case,
we're asking you to allow us to buy from
a Soul Source provider. They're the only
company that makes these membranes and
let us get started on that.
Second. Oh, yes. There'll be three
readings and Council Tina will be my
second question. Oh, I see it. Okay. I
have a quick question. Um, you mentioned
that the current membranes are from 2002
and that's longer than the normal
lifespan. What is the typical lifespan?
A normal lifespan would be 7 to 10
years. Um, part of the reason they
lasted so long at Southwater Plant was
we weren't running the plant at full
capacity. So, we had membranes in
storage down there that we've started to
use. So, those membranes are probably
they've been they were stored for a long
time and put in. So, they're probably 5
to seven years old in um operation as
Darren rotates through the at the full
time capacity. At full capacity. Um so,
there's four skids down there. They each
have membranes in them and he rotates
the skids. So, it's not at full
capacity, but he's using each skid now.
Okay. Thank you.
That's all I had. Any other questions?
Yep. Thank you. All right. Thank you.
Next is temporary resolution 5125, a
resolution stating the
service services to be provided by the
municipal corporation to the annex
territory of Euing Woods LLC for the
expedited type 2 annexation of parcel
number
027003600 consisting of uh 0.605 605
plus or minus acres in Pleasant Township
and to declare an emergency coming from
economic development committee.
Councilman Hope. Um yes, thank you. This
is a tiny piece of land that the owner
um decided to sell last minute. So,
they're going to annex it so it doesn't
create um an island. Um and so this is
just the first um step by adopting a
statement of services provided
um by Lancaster and it's along Sheridan
Drive. Okay. And
there's Well, Director Hall, is there
anything else? No. Um I would just note
the names look different because uh
previously um it was Hodgej and Underh
Hill doing this annexation uh on behalf
of themselves as the developers but now
they have a residential developer
attached that's Castow residential
development and they have named the
project Euing Woods LLC. So the
petitioner is different just because
they now have moved to the point where
they have a residential developer for
the project. Okay. Thanks. Thank you.
And so this is going to be just one
reading because of the timing. Um, and
Mr. Wing will be my second. Okay. Very
good. Any other questions?
Thank you.
Temporary resolution
52-25, a resolution to amend permit
resolution 21-25 authorizing the service
safety director to advertise for bids
and enter enter into a contract for the
construction of a maintenance and
storage facility for use by the Lanster
Fire Department and to declare an
emergency. Uh coming from the safety
committee, uh Councilman Bisjuk. Uh
thank you, Mr. Chair. Uh, Council Member
Tiner is going to be my second on the
legislation. Uh, what this legislation
is seeking to do is essentially increase
the upper limit of what can be spent on
this project from 360,000 to
660,000. Uh, I do want to emphasize that
this legislation is not an
appropriation. It's just increasing that
limit. Uh, mainly because the bid that
came in from Ever Saul Builders uh came
in for about 599,000. So, that's what's
going to happen. I am going to ask uh
for suspension for the second and third
readings tonight uh once it proceeds to
the full body. Um but that's what's
happening with this legislation. Okay.
This money though is this is un
unbudgeted money. Correct. Correct.
So this is unbudgeted money from the 51
account taxpayer dollars. And as slate
here I have some questions to ask.
So he's coming up now.
So, how big is this? How big is this um
building? What's the square footage?
Well, good evening and thank you for the
question. The the structure that we are
wanting to build behind station 3 is a
4,800 square foot pole building. Um
built to commercial standards, a little
bit different than someone might build
behind their house. um thicker concrete
reinforced um with heating and some of
the infrastructure for welding and some
of the maintenance things that we'll
need to be doing in the building. So,
where are you doing the maintenance now
on the vehicles?
Well, last Tuesday we had an issue with
pump 8, our reserve truck. A drain was
clogged up and it was leaking water. So,
Assistant Chief Moore changed clothes,
got on a creeper, and was underneath the
truck out in front of engine house 3.
Um, fortunately, it was a nice day out,
so he was able to do that without it
raining or um, you know, being real cold
out while they also did some maintenance
to the wireless headcom or headset
system. So, right now, wherever we can
find space, but the most recent example
was on the ground in front of station 3.
Okay. But you you've been inside of a
Haven't you been inside of a building
before doing work? Isn't there wasn't
there a building you guys were talking
about you could do maintenance inside of
a building?
The building that we're asking to build,
correct? No, another building that you
guys have been doing maintenance in
because I thought I remembered when we
had our meetings, you guys said there
was a building you guys were able to
use. There's that is correct. There's a
building that we the city I don't know
the history of how we acquired them.
There were um along Lawrence Street on
right by the wastewater treatment plant.
Uh the building itself is barely big
enough to get the fire apparatus in and
close the doors. Um we have no running
water, no facilities, no bathrooms down
there. Um so it's not conducive to do
maintenance, but if we had to to find a
place out of the rain, I guess we could.
Okay. Because I thought there was some
This is just kind of my problem. This is
this is over half a million dollars.
That's correct. And is there any way
that you could um go down from 4,800
square foot to lessen the cost? Because
you know, you guys also want a firehouse
and I'm hearing it's up to three
firehouses you want, not just one. And
this is taxpayer dollars. This is
unbudgeted money. Uh and this 251, isn't
the police department in this budget,
too? Aren't that their money's in there
also? Okay. Well, I'll try to address
all your questions. one with the three
firehouses. No, the strategic plan I've
asked for is relocating two. Um, as for
the size of the building, uh, no, this
the building is being kept under 5,000
square foot because Ohio fire code and
building codes will require a
suppression system and would would
add$100 to $200,000 to the cost. Um, by
building it where we're at, we were able
to eliminate the needs for a restroom,
um, some things like that because it's
right next to the firehouse. Um, 4,800
foot gives us enough room to have four
bays. That's four bays. one to put the
brand new smokehouse that we purchased
in this year that it was $110,000
investment. Another purchase from last
year. Yes. Um when the new medic arrives
later in July, we'll have an area to put
two medics because we're going to put
them back to back. So, we're down to
having two spaces left. Excuse me. And
then we have one back reserve fire
engine. So, that leaves me one empty
bay. So for future growth or for another
fire apparat so we could keep it in
reserve. It's still in good working
order. Um it would be nice to keep that
one extra bay open. U as far the funds.
Yes, it was budgeted at
360,000 based on our best guess when
this project began back in October of
2023. Um we proceeded and had support of
council to purchase property next door.
So it was difficult for us to know
exactly how much site work was going to
be involved with the project when we
were kind of initially budgeting for it.
Um so the 360 did was in the 247 which
is a fire levy account for I'm sorry a
safety levy between police and fire. Uh
the 251 has um the most carryover of the
three levy budgets that I have available
to me and was the budget that I was
asked to put in legislation.
Okay. So the now we'll go back to the
police. So that that is part of their
budget also that you're taking out of it
is a safety forces budget. The safety
forces budget. Now last year and I'm
going to go back. You mentioned the
firehouse. Thank you. Uh the smokehouse
that was purchased last year that was
over $100,000. Yes, it was. Okay. And
not to mention, you know, I mean I mean
I remember last year somebody took the
PNC card, spent $24,000 on workout
equipment for the firehouses. I mean,
it's just seems like there's just always
constantly something going on here with
with the the money, you know, in the
police department. My goodness, they got
a garage door for a the fire h or the
police station that was over 45 years
old and people some people lost their
crap over that. But, I mean, I just
don't I think this is a a want and not a
need in my opinion. And you know, if you
guys want firehouses and all this stuff,
I mean, this is this is taxpayer dollars
and this is unbudgeted. I would just
suggest maybe wait until the budget in
December and you know, try again. I I
mean, this is just money that, you know,
what happen if something else comes up
you're going to need. I I just don't
think this is necessary. I really don't.
Well, it in the budget that I inherited
from the last
administration, excuse me, we we do
build in contingencies for these
unexpect unexpected things that come up.
This is a project that we've been
working on for over two years and it it
was underestimated and I I have respect
for, you know, the idea of waiting until
the first of the year, but as everybody
knows, they see the the prices of
construction, you know, impacts of
tariffs on some of the materials. This
is just going to cost the taxpayers more
money by waiting until next year
potentially. Well, um
I Tom, you've been you and I have been
on council together for quite a while.
I I mean I'm going to channel him. Um
can you explain anything about like the
251 accounts or anything like that to
Well, I I think we're actually talking
about piece 53, not piece 52, right?
Because 53 is the one where we're
appropriating more money, right? This is
just this is basically upping the bid
price. So we're talking about 5325.
So all
right, since you asked, I'm going to
give you my honest opinion. Last year,
Steve Mappen stood at that podium and
had an overtime issue. Okay. And I can't
remember it was either 180 or 300. The
first one was over 100,000. What was it?
Does anyone remember the number? It was
a big number on what? Last year the
overtime issue with fire.
a big number that I remember I had asked
him uh well what's your next surprise
coming for the council in in 2024 but it
was a big number it was it was it was
six digits it was a big number yeah and
so it it and chief I understand you
inherited the budget but at the end of
the day what's the point of a budget if
we don't adhere to it right and I don't
disagree with what Becky just said as
far as about being a want a want being
meaning so much that if you waited until
next year and got it appropriated at
that time, you're still going to do the
project. Yeah, potentially it could cost
more and potentially it couldn't, right?
We we can always walk up there and say
that. But my my personal opinion is it's
a budget problem and you're asking and
Joe, it's not true. It is a
reappropriation of new money or an
appropriation of new money in in 53,
which I'm sure uh is you're going to
talk about next. So, it is money that
wasn't in the budget. So, let's not play
pretend, okay? It's it it is a new
appropriation for
$300,000. Now, unfortunately for me, I
didn't have money, so I couldn't
consider these things on a want basis.
We did everything on a need basis. And
you know that because you were here. All
right. Now, we're in a position where
we're flushed with flushed with cash.
And the only thing I'd say are two
things. It's a budget for a reason. All
right. And if we we let people come and
run to the podium for more money. We
just gave water department another half
million dollars, right? And we didn't
get really a full answer to Christina's
questions, which was, are we at full
capacity? Well, no, we're not at full
capacity, but we're running all four
kids. Well, what capacity are we? Are we
at 50%? Are we at 60%? Are we at 70%?
What are we? They She deserves an
answer.
So since you asked the question and I
formerly was the the finance chairman my
fundamental issue with this it's you
live with the budget that you have not
your fault but if we give if they give
you I have no vote here then we're
basically saying last year's math
problem one was okay and we're also now
saying last year problem math and two is
okay and if I was sitting in that chair
and I never will But I I wouldn't even
have had it introduced. That's that's my
that's my honest opinion. Yeah. So, and
you know, I I mean I just I I was I kind
of budget like with the city I think
about, you know, even at my home, you
know, what can I afford? What can I not?
What's norm what is I haven't had cable
television for 20 years because you know
what? I can't afford it. And and and I
know that's a little thing to mention.
This is I know this is but this is I
just don't think to me I I mean it's
like want want and give give and I think
some things we just kind of need to
backtrack on and just kind of
wait you know I mean I was okay with the
other amount but I just think this half
a million is a
lot he
uh Mr. Mr. Chair, I just want to
clarify. I'm only speaking about
5225, which was not an appropriation. I
understand 5325 is an appropriation. I
was only speaking to to 5225. So, I just
want to clarify that for the record. I I
do understand the difference between the
legislation. So, I just wanted to make
that clear to everybody in the room. So,
thank you,
Chairman Wolfinger, if I could. Yes. So,
I can't disagree with either points
Becky made or Tom made, but what I would
say is this.
No one I've spoken with, including Tom,
disputes the building is necessary. Why
is the building necessary? Yeah, we've
got a building that we can barely fit
our apparatus in down off Lawrence
Street that has no facilities to do
anything with. We have firefighters
laying out in the weather, working on
vehicles in all kinds of inclement
weather. We got lucky last week. There
are times when they're out there
underneath uh in pouring rain just to
make sure the apparatus is ready to go.
our backup uh fire apparatus are stored
offsite. So, we have to go to another
location to get apparatus to respond to
a call should the number one primary
vehicle be
down. I think it's a safe bet that if we
wait to next year, I don't know that
anyone in this room can dispute that the
price is going up. That's taxpayer
money. We have money in the 201
budget available to safety forces to pay
for this. If council chooses to wait
till next year, that's fine. I can I can
respect that. But think
about what we need as a facility upgrade
to house multi-million dollar
apparatus that we want to make sure are
there when we need them.
Now I've got to get into probably Chief,
how do you go pick up a backup apparatus
when your primary one's down? It takes
at least two people and then we have to
go down. We access the building um when
we have, you know, a driver to take us
there to open the building up, grab the
grab the apparatus, um and then take it
to whatever location that it might be
needed. In the meantime, the emergency
is still ongoing. It that is correct.
You know, when we have an emergency call
in and this happens, um when there's a
large incident that will be tied up for
a while, the fire department doesn't
stop receiving 911 calls for service.
So, we'll call in the medic unit, which
is behind medic 3 at station three,
ready to go. The fire apparatus,
however, is not that quick to put in
service. We have to go pick it up, uh
bring it back to the firehouse. When we
get enough people, everybody's gone. We
need at least two of those people with
an extra vehicle just to go pick it up
and bring it to the firehouse to put
firemen and the immediate equipment on
it. So my opinion is I can't disagree
that the budget was not appropriately
funded for this piece this budget
item. However, I think we look at the
price and I think safety committee spoke
about this. It appears to be a fair
price for the product we're requesting.
It is actually cut down to the point
where there's no amenities in inside
this building. It is what we need to
store these vehicles, work on these
vehicles, and respond appropriately to
request for service. You know, we can
walk out a back door and get that back
up apparatus and be gone on the 911
call, whatever it might be. I understand
the concerns. I can't disagree with
them. But I think we're if we want to
talk about taxpayer money, we can spend
it today and save or we're likely to
spend you know my this is nothing but a
gut but another 10% next year. So for
for your consideration
I I was just going to ask about okay 48.
Okay. So how many how many bays did you
say is going to be there? Four. Well
again can you refigure and cut it down?
Do you have to have four? I mean,
seriously, I know understand what you
said, but you know, I mean, do you need
four? I don't know how much that would
take off the price. Well, that's maybe
maybe we should wait and come back and
tell us. Well, the need for four is
right now I have one, excuse me, one
fire engine, but
when council was generous enough to
purchase another fire engine, we're
going to have two in reserve that takes
that fourth bay. So, I can sell one of
those that's still in good reserve
status or start putting more trucks
outside, but I'll have that fourth bay
full uh potentially by the end of 2026
when the new fire apparatus arrives.
2026. That's 20. That's the end of next
year. Yeah. And that's another thing you
just got to we just appropriate another
engine. Um so I mean I I I just really
think you don't need four bays. It'll I
mean you could refigure things. You you
could do something to cut it down, but
when you got question I just just a
comment. Uh after our meeting, our
committee meeting, I went over to the
engineer's office and reviewed the
drawings as an architect. And after
seeing the drawings and what's going
into the building, the price that we got
for it is a very competitive price. I
mean, I mean, I agree with everything
that the mayor said, and I understand
where you guys are coming from,
but I can only tell you that prices are
going to be higher if we wait. Could be.
And the price Well, maybe. You never
know. I don't know. Yeah.
Do you have a question? I do not have a
question, but a comment just for
clarification. Um, one, the building
that they are using on South Lawrence,
um, one, it is out of the way, but two,
it is not it does not belong to the fire
department. It's actually a water
pollution control building. So, I just
wanted to clarify. It's not like the
fire department actually has a building.
They're just water pollution was trying
to squeeze them in and find them a place
to temporarily store some stuff because
there was nowhere to put it. So this has
been an ongoing need for many many
years. And then I also wanted to just
clarify that the building itself did
come in at the original budgeted price.
However, what we didn't plan for in the
previous budget was the actual site work
to go with the building. And that even
with a smaller building, I don't know
that you're going to see much of a cost
savings because a lot of it is in
concrete. they have to use 6 in concrete
and that's that's a really large bulk of
the price. Um, so I I appreciate
Councilman Tina your your thoughts on a
smaller blueprint, but I don't know that
it would really save that much. And I
also just again wanted to clarify that
the building itself came in what we
thought it was supposed to be. We just
forgot to anticipate the site work and
we weren't expecting that. So, thank you
Chairman Wolfinger. Any other questions?
Okay, thank you. Well, I guess you might
hang out. Oh, you just explained the
other one. I'm sorry. You just explain
the other one, too. Okay. Um, next is
temporary resolution 5325, a resolution
to appropriate from the unencumbered
balance in the 045 police and fire levy
202 uh 2021 funduh 2051.
the the amended certificate of
appropriations with the fearful county
auditor and to declare an emergency
coming from finance committee. Uh Mr.
Als, you'll be the second. Yes. And I
showed two readings and um this has been
pretty well discussed I believe. Uh any
other comments you wish to make or
anybody else?
Were you able to call all the council
people and talk to them about it? Were
you able to get a hold of everyone?
I was able to speak with uh nine of the
10 council members present tonight.
Thank you.
Okay, that is it for the
resolutions ordinances. Uh we have one
tonight. Uh temporary ordinance
26-25, an ordinance to accept a petition
for the annexation of 0.605 605 plus or
minus acres in Pleasant Town township
uh to consent to annexation and declare
an emergency coming from the economic
development committee. Councilman Hope
um yes um
this can I just wanted to make a
correction. This can go three readings.
It was one. Um, but this is a companion
piece to temporary resolution 5125 and
it's to accept the annex and proceed
with the
process. Director Hall, was there
anything else? Yeah, I just wanted to
explain. So, um, normally we do an
ordinance to accept a petition for
annexation to signal that we are
accepting the petition for annexation
and because we have agreed to accept it
per the pre-anexation agreement. Um, I
didn't do a pre-annexation piece for
this annexation because like um,
Councilwoman Hoop explained earlier, it
the the land around it had already been
annexed, right? There were two chunks.
One was a 45 acre chunk and then one was
a 5acre chunk. And there was a
pre-anaxation agreement on both of
those. Um, so I didn't anticipate this.
605 acres um, being an issue. My my
office manager put it in for one reading
because that's normally what we do. We
have 25 days to accept a petition based
on the expedited type 2 annexation law.
Um, but again here it doesn't really
make a difference because we're not we
didn't do a pre-annexation agreement.
Um, there's no issue with actually um,
accepting the annexation. So if you
wanted to go three readings, you can go
three readings. If you wanted to go two
readings, you can go two readings. If
you wanted to go one, you can go one.
Doesn't make a difference. But um,
that's why it says one because typically
that is what we do. We have 25 days. But
here we can we can work with that a
little bit. Thank your preference. I say
stick with three. I say stick with Well,
is there an issue because it says one?
Yeah. No. So, I say being a rule
follower, let's do three readings. You
could do three. Yeah. Okay. Thank you.
And then um Mrs. Craig says my second.
Okay. Thank
you. Um that concludes the legislation
for tonight. Any departmental updates?
I see no one walking
uh tonight's meeting prep. President
Porter.
Thank you, Chairman Wolfinger. We have
15 resolutions on for tonight's meeting
along with two ordinances. We have no
special presentations this evening.
Okay. Thank you. And any other items for
finance committee that anybody wishes to
discuss? I see no hands. And
So um I'm looking for a motion to
adjurnn. So moved.
Thank you. Second.
All right. We had over here. So um all
those in favor please signify by saying
I. I. Okay. We are adjourned and it is
uh 6:30 on the button. All right. Uh
tonight's regular council meeting will
convene promptly at 6:35.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
Hi, I'm Travis Markwood from the
Langster Fair County Chamber of
Commerce. Our focus is support, grow,
build community, and add value as we
educate and advocate local business
organizations. This month, we are really
excited to be chosen as the recipient of
the Buckeye Cares program. That means
Buckeye will make a generous donation to
us with every vehicle they sell this
month. From all of us at the Langster
Fairfield County Chamber of Commerce, we
say thank you, Buckeye.
[Music]
Please rise if you're able and join me
in a moment of prayer. God grant us the
serenity to accept the things that we
cannot change, the courage to change the
things we can, and finally the wisdom to
know the difference. I'll call uh the
May 19th, 2025 Lancaster City Council
meeting to order. Please join me in the
pledge of allegiance.
I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for it stands. One nation under
God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Please call the role. Mr. Als here. Mr.
Bisjack here. Mrs. Kates here. Mrs. Hoop
here. Mr. Lockenberg here. Mr. Mr.
Skunover here, Mr. Sully here, Miss
Tiner here, Mr. Wing here, and Mr.
Wolfinger here. Let the record
reflected, all 10 members of Lancaster
City Council are present this or present
this evening, excuse me,
reading and disposing of the journal.
Um, regular meeting minutes dated May
5th, 2025.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal. Second.
A motion and second to receive and file
the journal. All those in favor, please
indicate by saving saying I. I. All
those opposed, same sign. Now move to
the reports of city officials. Email
dated May 5th regarding uh 2025
regarding Republic service contract
public records request responded by
sanitation superintendent Sean Fowler.
Email dated May 13, 2025 regarding or
Euing Woods LLC expedited type two
petition for annexation submitted by law
director Hall and office manager Liz
Martins. Email dated May 16, 2025. Call
to action. Testimony needed of utility
payment bills submitted by law director
Hall.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials. Second. We have a motion and
a second to receive and file the reports
of city officials. All those in favor,
please indicate by saying I. I. All
those opposed, same sign.
Communications. Email dated May 5th,
2025 regarding liquor license for
KS117 LLC doing business as Pit Stop and
Lancaster submitted by High Division of
Liquor Control. mail dated um May 5th,
2025 regarding application to adjust its
distribution rates for the public
utilities commission of Ohio submitted
by Ohio Power Company A. Email dated May
6, 2025 regarding reszoning parcel
027003600 submitted by Amy Finn with
Castow. Email dated May 6, 2025
regarding Republic Services contract um
public records request submitted by Jake
Hef Hefron with Rumkey. Email dated May
13, 2025 regarding public records
requests for digitized building plans
andor other documents for Fair Play
Pizza Theater submitted by Benjamin
Brun. uh email dated May 5th, 19 or May
19th, 2025 regarding um guide to Ohio
Medicaid submitted by Sarah Breen with
Single Care.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
Second. We have a motion and a second to
receive and file the communications. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I. I. All those opposed, same sign. We
have no special presentations or awards
this evening. We have no petitions in
memorials. We now reach the time in our
meeting for permission of voters and
taxpayers to address council. Uh you
have three minutes to address council.
You do need to sign in at the podium and
state your name and address before you
begin your um Yes, members of council.
Thank you. Um, my name is Amy Schlake
and I live on Lan Rico Boulevard and I
did not know we were going to get into
such a healthy discussion about fire um,
equipment, but I came up because for the
last two weeks I wanted to uh, commend
the fire chief and the fire personnel
for two different things that happened
over the past two weeks. one is I do
have the group for individuals that are
disabled and their parents and providers
and we had fire safety is kind of a
issue. Um just like we met with the
police to talk about safety and if
there's an emergency we had the same
with um fire personnel. They brought the
truck. Um even though my son was not
able to voice a question, he was able to
follow all around the truck and all
around the um u medic. and so he was
able to understand and see
everything. More importantly, they
responded to a fire at my home. Um, so I
would not want them to have to wait to
go get another fire truck because every
minute does count. Um, and I was just
going to give a healthy reminder to
people that are driving, especially when
there's construction and you're down to
one lane on Main Street, um, and you're
blocking fire vehicles, that it's, you
know, it's really important that you get
to the side. But um they came, they were
very calming. Um and I'm a very prepared
person. I used two fire blankets and a
fire extinguisher and I was not not able
to get it out. Um so thank you very
much. Um because they were able to take
care of it. Um and so I helped contain
it, but I could not get the fire out. Um
so I do appreciate them and that's all I
wanted to say. So thank you. Thank you.
Is there anybody else that wishes to
address council at this time?
Seeing none, we thank you for coming in
attending tonight's
meeting. Reports of standing committees.
I have five finance committee meeting
minutes dated May 5th, 2025 submitted by
Mr. Wolfinger. Safety committee minutes
um dated May 10th, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Bisjack. Finance Committee M agenda
dated May 16, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Wolfinger. Water, water, pollution
committee agenda dated May 17, 2025,
submitted by Mr. Wing. And law committee
agenda dated May 19th, 2025, submitted
by Mrs. Crates.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees. Second. We have a
motion and a second to receive and file
the reports of standing committees. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I. I. I. All those opposed, same sign.
Reports of special committees. There are
no reports. There are no public hearings
this evening. We will now move on to the
reading of resolutions with the third
reading of resolutions beginning with
temporary resolution 3825.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into an
agreement for engineering services
associated with flow monitoring and to
be conducted with in the river valley
highland subdivision. sanitary sewer
system. This is through water water
pollution committee. Mrs. Wing or Miss
Wing and Miss Miss Oh my god. Mr. Wing
and Miss Tener. I'm so sorry. Council
member Wing. Yes. Thank you, Mr.
President. I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution number 38-25. Second. A
motion and second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution
3825. Discussion. Council member Wing.
Uh, yes. This is the authorization for
the sanitary sewer flow monitoring study
in the River Valley Highlands. $250,000
is the authorization and that does
include some contingency in case it we
go through some dry periods. So, as I
said before, pray for rain. Thank you.
Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kra,
yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Luenberg, yes.
Mr. Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Teener, yes. Mr. Mr. Wing. Yes. And Mr.
W. Yes. Temporary resolution passes 10
to zero. Temporary resolution 3925. A
resolution to increase receipts
appropriate funds in the wastewater
reserve fund 6029. amend their
certificate of other sources and
appropriations with the county auditor
and to authorize payment of bills and
within and now certificates for the Ohio
water development loan for the solids
handling facility upgrade project. This
is through um water water pollution
committee Mr. Wing and Mr. Als. Council
member Wing. Yes. Thank you, Mr.
President. I'd like to make a motion
that coun council pass and grow to enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution number 39-25.
Second. We have a motion, a second to
pass a gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution
3925. Uh discussion. Council member
Wing. Yes. This just appropriates the
funds for the solids handling facility
on Lord Street from the wastewater
reserve fund. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the RO. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kites,
yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Loenberg, yes.
Mr. Skunover, yes. Mr. Sie, yes. Miss
Ter, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger, yes. Temporary resolution
3925 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
resolution 4025, a resolution to
increase receipts, appropriate funds in
the storm water utility reserve fund
6019. Amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriations with the
county auditor and authorized payments
of bills within and now certificates for
the Ohio water development loan for the
East Main Street sewer separation
project. Again, this is through water
water pollution committee, Mr. Wing and
Miss Tiner. Council member Wing. Uh,
yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like
to make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution number 40-25.
Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
4025. Discussion. Council member Wing.
Uh, yes. Similar to last piece, this
appropriates money from the storm water
utility reserve fund for the uh East
Main Street sewer separation project.
Any further discussion? Hearing none,
please call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kit, yes. Mrs. Hoop,
yes. Mr. Lockenberg, yes. Mr. Skunover,
yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss Tiner, yes.
Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr. Wolfinger, yes.
Temporary resolution 4025 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary resolution 4125. A
resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding due to a sole source
provider for membrane replacement for
the upper hawking water pollution
control facility. Again, this is through
water water committee and then Mr. Wing
and Mr. Als Council Member Wing. Mr.
President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution number 41-25.
Second. We have a motion, a second to
pass from gross and enter upon the
written record, temporary resolution
4125. Uh discussion, council member
Wing. Uh yes. Now that phase two of the
Upper Hawking plant is up and running,
it's time to replace the membranes in
phase one. And the need for this piece
is because those membranes are only um
produced by MECOR. Okay. Thank you. Any
further
discussion hearing? None. Please call
the RO. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes.
Mrs. Kit, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Mr.
Lockenberg. Yes. Mr. Skunover. Yes. Mr.
Sully. Yes. Miss Tiner. Yes. Mr. Wing.
Yes. Mr. Wolfinger. Yes. Temporary
resolution 4125 passes 10 to zero.
Temporary resolution 4225.
A resolution to authorize the city of
Lancaster to apply for funding from the
Ohio Department of Development for CHIP
programs funds. This is through economic
development committee. Mrs. Hoop and
Mrs. Kates. Council member Hoop. Yes,
Mr. President. And I would like to make
a motion that council pass engross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 42-25.
Second. Sorry. We have a motion in a
second to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
4225. Uh council member Hoop. Any
discussion? Um no. This is just to apply
for the 2026 cycle um for the chip
funding. Thank you. Any further
discussion hearing? None. Please call
the role. Mr. Als yes. Mr. Bishek. Yes.
Mrs. Kes, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr.
Lockenberg, yes. Mr. Skunover, yes. Mr.
Sully, yes. Miss Ter, yes. Mr. Wing,
yes. And Mr. Wolfinger, yes. Temporary
resolution 4225 passes 10 to zero.
Temporary resolution 4325.
A resolution to amend the certificate of
appropriations with the county auditor.
Appropriate from the unencumbered
balance, increase receipts, complete a
fund transfer in the CDBG loan repay
revolving account fund 2075 and in the
community development block grant fund
2073 and declare an emergency. This is
through economic development committee
and Mrs. Hoop and Mr. Wing. Council
member Hoop. Um, yes, Mr. President. I'd
like to make a motion that council pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 43-25.
Second. We have a motion and second to
pass gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution
4325. Discussion. Council member Hoop.
Um no, this is just
um we have to spend program income
before the grant money. So, we're
putting this money into the budget so
that it can be spent. Thank you. Any
further discussion? Hearing none, please
call the RO. Mr. Ess. Yes, Mr. Bisjack.
Yes, Mrs. Kitz. Yes, Mrs. Hoop. Yes, Mr.
Lenberg. Yes, Mr. Scooter. Yes, Mr.
Sully. Yes, Miss Tiner. Yes, Mr. Wing.
Yes. And Mr. Wolfinger. Yes. Temporary
resolution 4325 passes 10 to zero.
Temporary resolution 4525. A resolution
to appropriate from the unencumbered
balance in the general fund.
increase receipts appropriate from the
unencumbered balance in the health
insurance management fund
7022 and the mener certificate of
appropriations with the county auditor.
Mr. Administrative Services Committee,
Mr. Luenberg and Mr. Bisjack. Council
member Luenberg. Thank you, Mr.
President. I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record resolution
number 45-2.
Second. Have a motion and a second to
pass and upon the written record
temporary resolution
4525. Discussion. Council member
Lockenberg. Yes. Uh thank you, sir. Uh
this year we've had an unusual number of
life insurance claims from the city
employees and this amount will help
cover for those and hopefully any future
that uh come in this year. Thank you.
Any further discussion? Hearing none,
please call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kes, yes. Mrs. Hoop,
yes. Mr. Mr. Lockenberg. Yes. Mr.
Skunover. Yes. Mr. Si, yes. Miss Tiner,
yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr. Wolfinger,
yes. Temporary resolution 4525 passes 10
to zero. We'll now move on to the second
reading of resolutions, beginning with
temporary resolution 4625. a resolution
to approve Lancaster's fiscal year 2025
community development block grant annual
action plan and statement of objectives
and to authorize the mayor to submit the
same to the US department of housing and
urban development. This is through
economic development committee Mrs. Hoop
and Mr. Skunover. Council member Hoop.
Yes, this is uh second of three
readings. Second of three readings on
temporary resolution
4625. Uh temporary resolution 4725,
a resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumber balance
and to amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriation with the
county auditor in the timber top tiff
fund
3060. This is through finance committee
Mr. Wolfinger and Mr. Als. Council
member Wolfinger. Uh thank you Mr.
President. I would like to make a motion
to suspend the rules and wave the third
reading
on temporary resolution number 47-25.
Second. Second.
We have a motion and a second to uh
to he wasn't here and I he has to be the
second on this one. Sorry. It's okay.
That's okay. It's okay. So, Mr. Als is
the second. Yeah. Exactly. So, um, we
have the motion to suspend. Any
discussion? Council member Wolfinger.
Uh, just briefly, this is an adjustment
for the auditor's office. Uh, um,
153,48241
uh, was needed to be put in the account
from last year. And if Auditor Nettles
has a question comment, sorry, I I
apologize. We were going over something,
but what was that? I'm so sorry. No,
you're you're okay. We're just on the
motion to suspend at this point. Is
there any on um temporary resolution
4725? Was there anything you needed to
add in relation to that one? No. Okay.
Thank you, Council Member Wolfing. Any
further discussion on the motion to
suspend hearing? None. Please call a RO.
Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bishek, yes. Mrs. Kra,
yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Lterberg, yes.
Mr. Skuner, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Teener, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. and Mr.
Wolfinger. Yes. The motion to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution 4725 passes 10 to
zero. Council member Wolfinger. Uh thank
you, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion the council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 47-25.
Second. A motion and a second pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary resolution 4725. Any further
discussion? No. Thank you. Uh hearing
none, please call the role. Mr. Als,
yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kit, yes.
Mrs. Hoff, yes. Mr. Lockenberg, yes. Mr.
Skoonover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Teener, yes. Mr. Wolfinger, yes. I'm
sorry, Mr. Wing. Yes. I jumped the head.
Sorry.
That's it. Thank you. Temporary
resolution 4725 passes 10 to zero. We'll
now move on to the first meeting of
resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 4825. A resolution to
authorize the service safety director to
participate in the Ohio Public Works
Commission state capital improvement
and/or local transportation improvement
programs to execute contracts as
required and to declare an emergency.
This is through public works committee,
Miss Tiner and Mr. Spielberg. Council
member Tiner. Mr. President, I'd like to
make a motion the council suspend it
rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution 4825.
Second. A motion and second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution
4825. Any discussion on the motion
suspend? I'll wait. Thank you. Any
further discussion? Hearing none, please
call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kra, yes. Mr. Mrs.
Hoop, yes. Mr. Luenberg, yes. Mr.
Scoover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss Ter,
yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr. Wolfinger,
yes. Motion to suspend the rules and
wave the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 4825 passes 10 to
zero. Council member Tiner. Mr.
President, I'd like to p make a motion
to p that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 4825. Second. We have a
motion a second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
resolution
4825. Discussion. Council member Tiner.
Yes. This was a piece for uh us to apply
for a grant and there was a piece
missing. So,
um to this will allow us to go ahead and
put this piece in place so we can
hopefully get this grant for our
project. Thank you. Any further
discussion? Hearing none, please call
the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack,
yes. Mrs. Kra, yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr.
Lockenberg, yes. Mr. Skunover, yes. Mr.
Sully, yes. Miss Teener, yes. Mr. Wing,
yes. And Mr. Wolfinger, yes.
Motion to pass engross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
4825 passes 10 to
zero. We now move on to temporary
resolution 4925.
A resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance. Amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriations with the
county auditor in the general
fund for the one-time strategic
community investments grant program and
to declare an emergency. This is through
finance committee, Mr. Wolfinger and Mr.
Sully. Council member Wolfinger. Uh,
first of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary resolution
4925. Temporary resolution 50-25.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding for a sole source
provider contract for membrane
replacement for the South Water plant.
This is through water water pollution
committee. Mr. Wing and Miss Tiner.
Council member Wing. This will be the
first of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary resolution 5025.
Mr. President, yes. Can I correct the
record on this? I I think earlier stated
that um this is just a sole source
request. The money for this uh request
is in the water budget. So, we're not
asking for money. We're just asking for
to be able to use the sole source
provider. I just want to make sure that
was clear. Okay. Thank you for that
point of clarification.
We'll now move on to temporary
resolution 5125.
A resolution stating the services to be
provided by the municipal corporation to
the annex territory of Euing Woods LLC
for the expedited type 2 annexation of
parcel number
027003600 0 consisting of
0.605 plus or minus acres in the
Pleasant Township and to declare an
emergency. This is through economic
development committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mr.
Wing. Council member Hoop. Um, yes, Mr.
President. I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 51-25.
Second. We have a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and wave the second
and third reading of temporary
resolution
51-25. Any further discussion on the
motion to suspend? Council. Thank you.
Uh, hearing no further discussion,
please call the role. Mr. Als
Mrs. Hoop yes Mr. Lockenberg yes Mr.
Skunover yes Mr. Sully yes Miss Tiner
yes Mr. Wing yes and Mr. Wolfinger yes
motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
resolution 5125 passes 10 to zero
council member who um yes Mr. President,
I'd like to make a motion that council
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
51-25.
Second. We have a motion in a second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
5125. Any discussion? Council member
who? Um, this was discussed in finance,
but this is just to establish the
services that the city will provide for
the annexation off of Sheridan Drive.
Thank you very much. Any further
discussion? Hearing none, please call
the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack.
Yes. Mrs. Kitz. Yes. Mrs. Hook. Yes. Mr.
Lockenberg. Yes. Mr. Skunberg. Yes. Mr.
Sully. Yes. Miss Teener. Yes. Mr. Wing.
Yes. And Mr. Wolfinger. Yes. Temporary
resolution 51-25 passes 10 to zero.
Temporary resolution 5225. A resolution
to amend permanent resolution 21-25
authorizing the service safety director
to advertise for bids and enter into a
contract for the construction of of a
maintenance and storage facility for use
by the Lancaster fire department and
declare an emergency. This is through
safety committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss
Tiner. Council member Bisjack. Thank
you, Mr. President. I move that council
suspend its rules and wave the second
and third readings for temporary
resolution 52-25.
Second. You have a motion and a second
to suspend the rules and wave the second
and third reading of temporary
resolution
5225. Any discussion on the motion to
suspend? No, Mr. President. Thank you.
Please call the RO. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bischack, yes. Mrs. Kates, yes. Mrs.
Hoop, yes. Mr. Loenberg, yes. Mr.
Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Tinder, yes. Mr. Wing, yes. And Mr.
Wolfinger, yes. Motion to suspend the
rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary resolution 5225
passes 10 to zero.
Council member Bisjack. Thank you, Mr.
President. I move that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 52-25. Second. We
have a motion and second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 5225.
Any discussion? Uh, as we discussed in
the finance committee, this is
increasing the limit from $360,000 for
the project to
$660,000. This is not an appropriation.
That is all. Thank you. Any further
discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role. Mr.
IS, yes. Mr. Bisch, yes. Mrs. Kra, yes.
Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Lenberg, yes. Mr.
Skunover, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Tiner, no. Mr. Wing, and Mr. Wolfinger,
yes. Motion to pass and gross and enter
upon the written record. Temporary
resolution
52-25 passes 9 to1.
Temporary resolution 5325.
A resolution to amend the permanent
resol I'm sorry 52 5325 53. Okay. I
apologize. No. A resolution to
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance in the 045 police and fire levy
fund 2021 fund
2051 to amend the certificate of
appropriations with the Fairfill County
auditor and to declare an emergency.
This is through finance committee Mr.
Wolfinger and Mr. ES. Council member
Wolfinger. The first of two readings.
First of two readings on temporary
resolution
5325. Now move on to the reading of
ordinances. There are no third readings
this evening. We will begin with the
second reading of temporary ordinance
2525. An ordinance to authorize the
mayor to acquire the permanent and
temporary right of way necessary for the
East 6th Avenue bridge over Feder's Run
replacement project. This is through
public works committee. Miss Tiner and
Mr. Luenberg. Council member Tiner.
Second of three readings. Second of
three readings on temporary ordinance
2525. We'll now move on to the first
reading. Temporary ordinance 2625
and an ordinance to accept a petition
for the annexation of
0.60 5 plus or minus acres in the
Pleasant Township. the con to consent to
annexation and to declare an emergency.
This is through economic development
committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Kates.
Council member Hoop. First of three
readings. Thank you. First of three
readings on temporary ordinance
2625. There's no tabled legislation this
evening. We now move on to unfinished
business. Is there any unfinished
business before council this evening?
Thank you. New business. Is there any
new business before council this
evening? I have um two notifications
from the Ohio Division of Liquor Control
for
KBS117, Inc. um doing business as Pit
Stop of Lancaster, permit number
4528805.
Law Director Hall, is there anything we
need to do with that notification? Um
yes, you either have to object to the
renewal or um you can agree to the
renewal. I actually reached out to Chief
Snyder um over two weeks ago when we got
the original notice and asked if there
had been um any incidents that you
should be aware of when you're making
that decision. Um and nobody had any
incidents that they that they responded
with. So I think you're probably good to
go. Okay. So do we need a motion or any
Sure. Yeah. Just a motion second and
then a vote. Majority. All right.
Council member Skinner, would you make a
motion that we allow the renewal to
proceed?
Uh, yes. Second. I'll make Let me make a
motion. I'll make a motion that we Thank
you. accept the renew the liquor
license. Second. Okay. We have a motion
and a second to accept the renewal of
the liquor license as read by the clerk.
Um, all those in favor, please signify
by saying I. I. I. All those opposed,
same sign. Thank you. Is there any one
more or is that it? That was it. Thank
you. Okay. Um, announcements of
scheduled meetings. I have next regular
sessions, uh, council sessions, uh, June
9th, 2025 at 6:30 p.m. here in council
chambers. June 23rd and 2025 at 6:30
p.m. And here in council chambers, no
special scheduled meetings. We'll move
to regularly scheduled committee
meetings. I have law committee May 23rd
at 9:00 a.m. City Hall 1897 conference
room. I have safety committee meeting
June 6th at 8:00 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room. Service committee June
13th at 8:00 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room. And then water water
pollution control service meeting June
13th at 9:00 a.m.
service city hall 1897 room. Thank you.
Reading of bills. I have two for MNCO.
One
$109.86 and another one is for $165.78.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
we pay the bills. Second. Motion and
second to pay the bills. All those in
favor signify by saying I. I. I oppose.
Same sign. Thank you. Bills are paid. No
need for an executive session. I will
entertain a motion to adjurnn. Mr.
President, I'd like to make that motion.
We adjourn. Second. Have a motion, a
second to adjurnn. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I. I. This
meeting of Lancaster City Council is
adjourned. Please remember to sign your
legislation before you leave.
[Music]